Evangeline Ensley Walton papers, 1936-1984
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Evangeline Ensley Walton papers, 1936-1984
MS 384
Walton, Evangeline Ensley
Collection consists of biographical clippings, correspondence, and manuscripts. Correspondence is divided into two categories, general and John C. Powys, Welsh novelist, essayist and poet. Separation listing of books can be found in the control folder.
.8 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Born Evangeline Ensley in 1907 in Indianapolis, Indiana, she published the first volumes of her Mabinogion trilogy, based on the book of Welsh legends, The Virgin and the Swine, in 1936. It was published in 1970 as The Island of the Mighty and followed by The Children of Llyr, The Song of Rhiannon, and The Prince of Annwn. Known as a fantasy writer with a large following in America and Europe, she also published Witch House (1945), The Cross and the Sword (1956), and Son of Darkness (1957). She moved to Tucson in 1940 where she passed in 1996.
Organization
This collection is organized into 3 Series
Series I: Biographical Materials, 1936-1996
Series II:Correspondence, 1937-1959
Series III:Manuscripts
Scope and Content Note
Collection consists of biographical clippings, correspondence, and manuscripts. Correspondence is divided into two categories, general and John C. Powys, Welsh novelist, essayist and poet. Separation listing of books can be found in the control folder.
Access Terms
Walton, Evangeline -- Archives.
Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963 -- Correspondence.
Women authors.
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.
Fantasy fiction,American.
Mythology,Welsh.
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Materials, 1936-1996
  - Biographical Clippings 1936-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - August Derleth, director of Arkham House, July 17, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - (continued) Publishers, to Evangeline Walton Ensley. Concerning the rights to The Virgin and the Swine. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Incomplete list of "inspirational" advice n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - John Milton Phillips, Minister of The First Church of Christ in Hartford, Connecticut to Ben (?) complimenting The Virgin and the Swine. April 12, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ben Abrams (?) of the Argus Bookshop Inc. in Chicago to Evangeline Walton Ensley August 8, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph (John C. Powys ?) April 14, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. December 14, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton complimenting The Virgin and the Swine. February 23, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. Incomplete letter with no date. February 27, 1937(?) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. March 6,1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. Apri l 20, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. June 19, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. August 4, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. October 23, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. December 31, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. April 20, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. July 31,1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. December 9, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. December 9 or 10, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. April 22,1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. August 19, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. January 22, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. January 19, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. February 13,1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. September 15, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. January 5, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton. December 10, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John C. Powys to Evangeline Walton.(continued) 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III: Manuscripts
  - Manuscript: Children of Llyr n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript: Children of Llyr n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript: Children of Llyr n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript: The Cross and the Sword n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript: The Cross and the Sword n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript: Prince of Annwn n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript: Song of Rhiannon n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript: Song of Rhiannon n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript: The Sword is Forged n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript: The Sword is Forged n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript: The Sword is Forged n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript: Witch House n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript: Witch House n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)